Guide to the Barbara Hammer Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings and personal papers, 1940-2017; Series I; 22.0; (25 boxes)
  - Writings by Barbara Hammer, circa 1997-2005 (Box 12)
    Includes: typescripts; photocopies of printed material; proposals; emails; holograph notes. Also includes: email correspondence with Florrie Burke.
  - Papers relating to "History Lessons", circa 2000-2001 (Box 12)
    Includes: typescript papers; photocopied/faxed press and promotional materials; email from Barbara Hammer.
  - Thank yous and other kind letters, circa 1998-2005; 2 folders (Box 12)
    Includes: emails, letters, cards, postcards, and notes. Also includes: email to Florrie Burke; other papers.
  - Travel to China, 2004 (Box 12)
    Includes: correspondence; travel documents; other papers.
  - Materials relating to film festivals entered by Barbara Hammer, circa 1991-2001 (Box 12)
    Includes: correspondence; programs; printouts; submission forms; other papers.
  - Promotional materials and printed images, circa 2002 (Box 12)
    Includes: promotional materials regarding exhibits; printed images featuring Barbara Hammer; flyers for Barbara Hammer visit.
  - Interviews, 2001-2004 (Box 12)
    Includes: typescripts; emails; online printouts; photocopies of printed material.
  - Letters from Barbara Hammer, circa 1999-2007 (Box 12)
    Includes: letters; email correspondence; postcard. Also includes: feedback form submitted by Barbara Hammer.
  - Letters to Barbara Hammer, circa 2000s (Box 12)
    Includes: letters; emails; cards; postcards; notes; other papers.
  - Papers relating to incomplete projects, circa 1990s (Box 13)
    Includes: project notes; newspaper clippings; proposal.
  - Distribution, circa 1989-2005 (Box 13)
    Includes: records, correspondence, notes, printed material, and other materials relating to distribution of films. Also includes: correspondence unrelated to distribution; printouts; newspaper clippings; other papers.
  - Influences, circa 2000-2009 (Box 13)
    Includes: newspaper clippings; holograph notes; printed material; typescript and photocopied material regarding John Greyson; promotional material for art exhibition.
  - Photos, circa 2000-2006 (Box 13)
    Includes: photoprints and printed images.
  - Career awards, circa 2000s (Box 13)
    Includes: Envelope for 2000 Frameline Award containing ticket stubs, post card announcement, news ad "close Up: Visionaries of Modern Cinema", Fax from Framelinefrom Modern Masters Award (2002) [6 leaves]; Brochure from frameline festival; handwritten intrudviton by Florrie Burke; brochure, 9th St. Independent Film with Photo of BH giving award; review of Tender Histories; Melbourne Queer Film Festival program [70 pages]; news photo of BH and host in Austrailia, photocopied press and flyer (9+ duplicates); email correspondence with Bill Schiller about Polar Bear Prize and "My Babushka" [3 leaves]; Shirley Clarke avant garde filmmkaer award [11 leaves] - intro plus transcription of event.; newspaper foldout on DIGit festival; Best of Show, "Resisting Paradise", DIGit [2 leaves]; 2 color printed images of Arts and Activism panel (2005) Williamsburg, Brooklyn; letter from IFP; brochure on feminism, video activism from Barbara Hammer and Martha Rolser (from Seoul, Korea, I-GONG) - [58 leaves].
  - Contracts, circa 2000-2009 (Box 13)
    Includes: contracts; financial materials; letters; title research report for "My Babushka: Searching Ukrainian Identities"; other papers.
  - Papers relating to website, circa 2000-2009 (Box 13)
    Includes: correspondence; notes; financial materials; printouts; other papers.
  - Notebook, circa 2003-2004 (Box 13)
  - Influences, circa 2002-2008 (Box 14)
    Includes: holograph notes; printed journal article; material relating to exhibitions; National Film Preservation Foundation report to the U.S. Congress; written testimony by Florrie Burke; other papers.
  - Contracts and contacts, circa 2008 (Box 14)
    Includes: contracts; typescript and holograph contact information.
  - Get well cards, 2006 (Box 14)
    Also includes: holograph note.
  - Letters to Barbara Hammer, circa 2001-2010 (Box 14)
    Includes: postcards; cards; letters; holograph notes; email correspondence. Also includes: printout programs for Zurich festival; other papers.
  - Awards, circa 2007-2009 (Box 14)
    Includes: programs, acceptance speech typescript, and correspondence relating to awards and grants. Also includes: photoprints; holograph notes; other papers.
  - Drawings, 2006-2011 (Box 14)
    Includes: photocopies of sketches with holograph notes.
  - Writing by Barbara Hammer, circa 2005-2009 (Box 14)
    Includes: typescripts; holograph notes. Also includes: photocopied writings by others; other papers.
  - Writings and lecture notes, circa 2006-2007 (Box 14)
    Also includes: email correspondence.
  - Book performance notes, 2009 (Box 14)
    Includes: typescript notes.
  - Programs and promotional materials, 1999-2010 (Box 14)
    Also includes: newspaper clipping; other papers.
  - Essay on Barbara Hammer, undated (Box 14)
    Includes: typescript essay by Caroline Koebel.
  - Photos, 2003-2008 (Box 14)
    Includes: photoprints and printed images; holograph note and letter from others.
  - "WACK! Art and the Feminist Revolution" exhibition, circa 2004-2009 (Box 14)
    Includes: programs, promotional materials, letters, typescript biography, press, and other papers relating to "WACK! Art and the Feminist Revolution" exhibition.
  - Press, circa 2004-2009 (Box 14)
    Includes: press clippings, photocopies, and printouts; periodicals. Also includes: promotional materials.
  - Programs, 2005-2010; 3 folders (Box 14)
    Includes: ten programs for film festivals and conferences. Also includes: publication accompanying art exhibition.
  - Notebooks, 2000s (Box 14)
    Includes: three spiral bound notebooks.
  - Notes from Cassis, France: Camargo Foundation, circa 1999-2000 (Box 14)
    Includes: notebook; address book and business cards; postcards; letters to Barbara Hammer; calendar.
  - Business cards and correspondence, circa 2004-2007; 3 folders (Box 14)
    Includes: business cards, mostly from overseas trips; letters to Barbara Hammer; other papers.
  - Programs, circa 2008-2011 (Box 15)
    Also includes: promotional materials; printouts regarding MoMA retrospective on Barbara Hammer.
  - Letters to Barbara Hammer, circa 2009-2011 (Box 15)
    Includes: letters, cards, postcards, notes.
  - International Experimental Media Congress, 2010 (Box 15)
    Includes: delegate guide, program, "further resources" sheet for 2010 International Experimental Media Congress in Toronto. Also includes: newspaper clipping relating to event featuring Barbara Hammer.
  - Event(s) relating to experimental medical films, circa 2010 (Box 15)
    Includes: programs; promotional materials; letters to Barbara Hammer; evaluation form; other papers.
  - Programs and catalogues, 2009-2012; 2 folders (Box 15)
    Also includes: poster with holograph notes to Barbara Hammer; zine regarding Yoko Ono.
  - Press, circa 2003-2011 (Box 15)
    Includes: periodicals; newspaper clippings and photocopies. Also includes: promotional material.
  - Reviews and interviews, 2010-2012 (Box 15)
    Includes: periodicals and newspaper clippings featuring reviews and interviews. Also includes: promotional materials; holograph note to Barbara Hammer.
  - Performances and other events, circa 2009-2010 (Box 15)
    Includes: programs, notes, promotional materials, press clippings, and other papers relating to Barbara Hammer performances and other events.
  - Lecture panels (Box 15)
    Includes: programs and bio relating to lecture panels.
  - Interviews, 2008, undated (Box 15)
    Includes: printout and typescript interviews with Barbara Hammer.
  - Writings by Barbara Hammer, circa 2008-2011 (Box 15)
    Includes: review of film by Brad Lichtenstein; typescript lecture; piece about "Vital Signs"; piece about ovarian cancer.
  - Photos and New Years card printout, 2011, undated (Box 15)
    Includes: photoprints of Barbara Hammer; printout New Years card from Barbara Hammer and Florrie Burke.
  - 'Hammer! Making Movies Out of Sex and Life' promotional material, circa 2010 (Box 15)
  - Printed material regarding lesbianism, 2002-2010 (Box 15)
    Includes: "Dyke Action Machine!" catalogue; "Les+" Chinese periodical; magazine clipping.
  - Articles and promotional material, 2009-2010 (Box 15)
    Includes: postcard set; printed periodical featuring piece about Barbara Hammer; booklet about Barbara Hammer; printout journal article regarding Barbara Hammer.
  - Influences, circa 2010-2011 (Box 15)
    Includes: holograph note; booklets and signed poster relating to "Community Action Center"; promotional material for exhibition; printed clippings.
  - Awards, circa 2009-2011 (Box 15)
    Includes: letters; certificates; programs; promotional material; printed material.
  - Certificate and diplomas, 1963-1987 (Box 16)
    Includes: The Statue of Liberty Ellis Island Foundation, Inc. certificate for Anne Buchack Kusz; Barbara Hammer diplomas from San Francisco State College and San Francisco State University.
  - Awards, circa 1983-2012 (Box 16)
    Includes: certificates of award and participation; letters regarding awards; programs for awards ceremonies; ribbons. Also includes: other typescript and printed material.
  - Programs, catalogs, and promotional material, circa 2012 (Box 16)
    Also includes: newspaper segment featuring Barbara Hammer.
  - Exhibitions: promotional material, programs, notes, and correspondence, 2010-2013 (Box 16)
    Also includes: promotional material for 'Hammer!' film and other events.
  - Correspondence, circa 2012-2013 (Box 16)
    Includes: letters, cards, postcards, and emails, mostly from others to Barbara Hammer. Also includes: watercolor and pastel artwork.
  - Grants, 2012-2013 (Box 16)
    Includes: grant awards; correspondence relating to grants; application materials.
  - Contracts and releases, 2012-2013 (Box 16)
    Also inclues: printed booklet and promotional material relating to The Academy Museum of Motion Pictures; letters.
  - Press, 2012; 2 folders (Box 16)
    Includes: periodical clipping; online printout; newspaper with holograph note; magazine with holograph note.
  - Writings, circa 2012-2013 (Box 16)
    Includes: typescript writing; review of 'Blue Is the Warmest Color'; zine; printed journal. Also includes: typescript introduciton for Barbara Hammer.
  - Programs and promotional materials for events featuring Barbara Hammer, 2012-2013 (Box 16)
    Also includes: email correspondence; catalog.
  - "Bend a Bow" exhibition, 2012 (Box 16)
    Includes: exhibition booklet with holograph note.
  - Influences, circa 2009-2013 (Box 16)
    Includes: promotional materials; newspaper clippings; exhibition booklets; periodicals; catalogue; programs; typescripts; holograph notes; other papers.
  - "Lesbians in the West Village" printout, undated (Box 16)
  - "Barbara Hammer: The Fearless Frame" exhibition at Tate Modern, 2011-2012 (Box 16)
    Includes: programs; promotional materials; typscript and holograph notes; newspaper clippings; other typescripts.
  - Event materials, circa 2011-2013 (Box 16)
    Includes: promotional materials, programs, correspondence, financial materials, tickets, itinerary, typescript information packets, and newspaper clippings relating to events featuring Barbara Hammer, including retrospectives.
  - Festival programs, 2012-2014 (Box 16)
    Includes: four printed programs.
  - Reviews, 2012-2013 (Box 16)
    Includes: periodical clippings and photoopy; typescript; printed journal including article about Barbara Hammer. Also includes: holograph note with photoprint to Barbara Hammer.
  - Award ceremony programs and clippings, 2015-2016 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence and notes related to conference appearances, 2015 (Box 17)
  - Contracts related to sales of artworks by Hammer, 2015-2016 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, promotional material, and ephemera related to art exhibitions featuring Hammer's work, 2014-2016; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Correspondence and paperwork related to grant applications, 2013-2014 (Box 17)
  - Festival programs and promotional materials, 2014-2016; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, notes, and promotional material related to installations of Hammer's works, 2014 (Box 17)
  - Lecture notes and related promotional materials, 2014-2016 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence to and from Barbara Hammer, 2015; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Influences, 2011-2015 (Box 17)
  - Press releases and promotional material for performances, 2013-2016 (Box 17)
  - Reviews and clippings, 2012-2015 (Box 17)
  - Teaching notes and related materials, 2015 (Box 17)
  - Event programs containing writing about or by Barbara Hammer, 2015- (Box 17)
  - Transcript of Russell Scheaffer's film shoot of "Masculinity/Femininity" at Barbara Hammer's studio, 2015 (Box 17)
  - Project ideas, 2015 (Box 17)
  - Writings, clippings, and research related to Hammer's book draft, circa 1980-2005; 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Journals and notebooks, 1952-1968; 6 folders (Box 19)
  - Journals and notebooks, 1970-1979; 23 folders (Box 20)
  - Journals and notebooks, 1979-1990; 27 folders (Box 21)
  - Journals and notebooks, 1990-2011; 34 folders (Box 22)
  - Correspondence and love letters, 1978-2005; 17 (Box 23)
    Contains correspondence to and from multiple individuals including: Dorothy Weicker, Terry Sendgraff, Batya Bauman, Renate Duelli-Klein Cecily Cecil, Florrie Burke, Marsha Friedman, and Gloria Churchman.
  - Photographs of Barbara Hammer and others, circa 1975-2015; 3 folders (Box 24)
  - Speech notes, undated (Box 24)
  - Reviews, clippings, and flyers, 1992-2001 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence from Barbara Hammer to Florrie Burke, circa 1990s (Box 24)
  - Film festival programs and ephemera, circa 1991 (Box 24)
  - Notes and cards to Barbara Hammer, 1986; undated (Box 24)
  - Press clippings and film stills, 1957-2004 (Box 24)
  - Hammer family tree documentation and photographs, 1959-1992 (Box 24)
  - Drawings, 1976-1999 (Box 24)
  - Photographs and film stills, undated (Box 24)
  - Influences, circa 1979-2015 (Box 24)
  - Photographs of Hammer and others, undated (Box 24)
  - Programs and ephemera from Hammer's trip to Ukraine, circa 2000 (Box 24)
  - Notes and ephemera, circa 2007 (Box 24)
  - Birthday cards, 2017 (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 2016-2017; 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Documents related to Barbara Hammer's schooling and teaching experiences, 1947-1993 (Box 25)
  - Photographs of and by Hammer, 2004-2005 (Box 25)
  - Influences, 2016-2017 (Box 25)
  - Masculinity/Femininity supplemental booklet, 2016 (Box 25)
- Film projects, artwork, and research, 1980-2017; Series II; 11.33; (17 boxes)
  Contains materials related to Barbara Hammer's work as a filmmaker and artist including writings, project files, research materials, event documentation, correspondence, ephemera, and clippings.
  - Camargo Foundation fellowship application, 1999 (Box 26)
  - Notes and correspondence related to "Resisting Paradise" colloquium, circa 1999-2000 (Box 26)
  - "Resisting Paradise" research notes, 1994-1996 (Box 26)
  - Notes and correspondence related to the costs and production of "Resisting Paradise", 2002; 4 folders (Box 26)
  - Grant applications and documentation, 2000-2005 (Box 26)
  - Guggenheim fellowship application materials, 1999-2004 (Box 26)
  - Bunting Institute application materials, 1997-2001 (Box 26)
  - Press, correspondence, and documentation related to "Resisting Paradise", 2001-2004; 12 folders (Box 26)
  - Biographical materials for Barbara Hammer, circa 2004-2006; 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Festival programs and clippings, 2003 (Box 26)
  - Contracts, permissions, and release forms for Hammer films, circa 1988-2010; 4 folders (Box 26)
  - Promotional images and flyers for "Resisting Paradise" and other Hammer films, circa 2000-2003 (Box 27)
  - Cover designs for DVD releases of Hammer films, circa 2000's (Box 27)
  - Research materials for "Nitrate Kisses", circa 1990's (Box 27)
  - Text for "Nitrate Kisses", undated (Box 27)
  - Promotional material, correspondence, and documentation related to "Last year at Villa Serbelloni", 2001-2003 (Box 27)
  - Press, reviews, and clippings for "Nitrate Kisses", 1992-1996; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Notes, contracts, correspondence, and clippings related to "The Female Closet", 1991-1998; 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Reviews, clippings, research, and notes related to "History Lessons", circa 2000s; 6 folders (Box 28)
  - Press releases and clippings for "Tender Fiction", 1993-1997; 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Installation notes and press for "8 in 8" installation, 1994 (Box 28)
  - Research and notes for "Nancy Drew Investigates Breast Cancer", undated (Box 28)
  - Notes and press clippings for "Vital Signs", 1992 (Box 28)
  - Notes and fliers for workshops and lectures by Hammer, 1992-2011 (Box 28)
  - Videography/filmography lists, correspondence, and application materials, circa 1997-2001; 4 folders (Box 28)
  - Thank you letters, 2005-2011 (Box 28)
  - Pamphlets and information regarding artist residencies, 1989-2004 (Box 29)
  - Application materials for funding and residencies, circa 1990s-2003; 3 folders (Box 29)
  - Contracts and permissions, 1985-2011 (Box 29)
  - Application materials and correspondence related to the National Endowment for the Arts funding, 1992-1995 (Box 29)
  - Resumes for crew members, undated (Box 29)
  - Writings and correspondence by Hammer and others, 1980-2001; 4 folders (Box 29)
  - Correspondence, notes, clippings, and documentation related to "Devotion", circa 1999-2005; 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, notes, clippings, and documentation related to "Devotion", circa 1998-2000; 2 folders (Box 31)
  - Contracts, releases, and distribution documentation for "Devotion", circa 1994-2000 (Box 32)
  - Notes and documentation related to "Tokens and Trinkets", circa 1997-2001; 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Notes, clippings, and ideas for autobiography, circa 1989-1995 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence related to film projects, 2003-2004 (Box 32)
  - Correspondence and documentation related to events and presentations at Radcliffe, circa 2003-2008 (Box 33)
  - Dialogue, translations, and subtitles for film projects, undated; 2 folders (Box 34)
  - Press packets, clippings, and programs related to "Lover Other", 2005-2007; 5 folders (Box 34)
  - Kristin Poor's thesis on Claude Cahun and Marcel Moore, undated; 3 folders (Box 34)
  - Background research, documentation, and notes related to "Loving Other", undated; 3 folders (Box 34)
  - "I Am in Training" script by Laurie Collyer, 2003 (Box 34)
  - Programs and catalogs for "My Babushka", 2001 (Box 35)
  - Correspondence and press for "My Babushka", circa 2001-2006; 2 folders (Box 35)
  - Research and notes about Ukraine for "My Babushka", circa 2000-2002; 2 folders (Box 35)
  - Research and clippings for "Nitrate Kisses", circa 1987-1991 (Box 36)
  - Press and clippings for "Nitrate Kisses" and "Tender Fictions", circa 1997 (Box 36)
  - Grant proposal for "My Babushka", 1997 (Box 36)
  - Research for "Generations", 2007-2009 (Box 36)
  - Research, correspondence, and clippings for "My Babushka", circa 1996-1997 (Box 36)
  - Research, clippings, and notes related to pornography and "History Lessons", circa 1984-1997 (Box 36)
  - Booklet for "Desire" at ICA London, 1984 (Box 36)
  - Photocopied clippings for research, undated (Box 36)
  - Correspondence, notes, and treatment for "History Lessons", circa 1997 (Box 36)
  - Research, slides, and notes for "Resisting Paradise", circa 2002; 2 folders (Box 36)
  - Research, articles, and clippings on Walter Benjamin, circa 2004 (Box 37)
  - Notes, press, programs, and research related to "Resisting Paradise", 1999-2004; 4 folders (Box 37)
  - Contracts and production documentation related to "Resisting Paradise", 2003-2004 (Box 37)
  - Photographs collected during "Resisting Paradise" research process, undated; 4 folders (Box 37)
  - Photographs collected during "Female Closet" research process, undated (Box 37)
  - Correspondence related to "Female Closet", 1995-1996 (Box 37)
  - Research about Hannah Hoch for "Female Closet", circa 1996-1997; 2 folders (Box 37)
  - Research notes, correspondence, photographs related Alice Austen for "Female Closet", circa 1996-1997; 5 folders (Box 37)
  - Badges, lanyards, and ephemera from events and film festivals, circa 1980s-2015; 9 folders (Box 38)
    Contains nametags, badges, lanyard, pins, postcards, and other ephemera from events and film festivals attended by Barbara Hammer.
  - Photographs and film stills related to "Resisting Paradise", undated; 32 folders (Box 39)
  - Correspondence related to awards, 2017 (Box 40)
  - Programs, postcards, and correspondence related to exhibitions, circa 2016; 2 folders (Box 40)
  - Itineraries and documentation related to lectures given by Hammer, 2016 (Box 40)
  - Exhibition programs for Hammer retrospectives, 2016 (Box 40)
  - Writings about Hammer, circa 2016 (Box 40)
  - Programs, badges, and documentation related to events and film festivals attended by Hammer, circa 2016; 3 folders (Box 41)
  - Score sample for "Evidentiary Bodies", undated (Box 41)
  - Artwork related to "Lover Other: Claude Cahun and Marcel Moore", undated; 4 rolls (Box 42 (Oversize))
  - Korea research--publications, notes, transcripts, 1997-2007; 6 folders (Box 43)
  - Research material on Claude Cahun and Marcel Moore, ca. 2003-2005; 1 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence with Aube, Leperlier, Mlle Catala, residents of Jersey and unrelated photographs, 30-11-2004 (Box 44)
  - Devotion transcripts in English and Japanese, undated (Box 44)
  - Propaganda - Cahun/Moore - photocopies of research material, undated (Box 44)
  - SISTER/RESISTERS/LOVERS/OTHERS script drafts, 2004; 1 (Box 44)
- Teaching notes, 1970-2010; Series III; 7.58; (7 boxes)
  Contains materials related to Barbara Hammer's work as a teacher including lecture notes, syllabi, writings by others, and documentation related to Hammer's employment at various institutions.
  - Teaching materials, 1970s (Box 45)
  - Lecture notes, circa 1980s (Box 45)
    Includes: notecards with lecture notes; typescript script for lunar yoga guidance; photocopied audience responses to "Women I Love".
  - Papers relating to teaching (Box 45)
    Includes: correspondence; filmographies; fliers for classes; pther papers relating to classes taught by Barbara Hammer.
  - Applications materials for Artist Mentor Project, 1995 (Box 45)
  - Material relating to panels, workshops, and classes with Barbara Hammer, circa 1992-1994 (Box 45)
  - EGS summer class, 2006-10 (Box 45)
    Includes: emails and notes relating to EGS summer class.
  - Lecture notes on identity politics, undated (Box 45)
  - Research and notes on women filmmakers, circa 1983-2010; 2 folders (Box 45)
    Contains research and notes on women filmmakers including Alice Guy Blaché, Germaine DuLac, Gunvor Nelson, Chick Strand, Mary Ellen Bute, Carolee Schneemann, Marie Menken, Joyce Wieland, Yvonne Rainer, Sharon Cousin, Maya Deren, Leni Riefenstahl, and Shirley Clarke.
  - Syllabi for courses taught by Hammer, circa 1988-1994 (Box 45)
    Includes syllabi for courses taught by Hammer at the New School and San Francisco Art Institute.
  - Notes, research, and documentation related to Hammer's teaching, circa 1982-1999; 2 folders (Box 45)
  - Student evaluations of Hammer's teaching, circa 2005 (Box 45)
  - Correspondence and research related to women filmmakers, circa 19080-1988 (Box 45)
  - Notes and research related to Hammer's teaching, circa 2001; 2 folders (Box 45)
  - Teaching applications and recommendation letters, circa 1982-1992 (Box 45)
  - Feminist filmmaking syllabi and notes, circa 1983-1989 (Box 45)